So there's going to be many times on
this course that I take you through good
principles for effective AI agentic
engineering. And we're going to start
now with the sort of basic five big
ideas for successful vibe coding. And it
all comes under the heading be the boss.
The first one is one we've already
talked about which is about spending
time on your agents or MD. You want it
to be concise and you want to cover
importantly three different areas. You
want to spec what needs to be done very
clearly. You want to describe the style
that it needs to be done in and you need
to be explaining what it means to be
successful so that it's absolutely clear
how to gauge success at the end of it.
That would be a good concise clear
agents.mmd. You need to start your
project simple, straightforward, easy.
And I'm not just saying that that in
your agents.md you begin the first
section with something that's that's
easy. I'm saying your entire project,
your first agents.mmd should itself just
be the very basic MVP. Begin by building
something basic in your whole
agents.mmd. Go through that entire
iteration, including testing it at each
point, including substeps. Make sure
that it works and then decide to take it
a step more complex. If you try and
start by boiling the ocean with a super
complicated application spelt out in
your agents.mmd, then you might go off
track, off the rails. It might not work
and you'll just get stuck. So start
simple. And obviously that goes along
with that is to then work incrementally,
constantly testing, constantly
validating the success criteria at each
step. If you're working in this very
regimented way, this disciplined way,
then you can guarantee at each point
that you've reached that that milestone
successfully, and you can always go back
if you haven't. And then, you know,
these all sort of belong together, but
but don't get lazy. Avoid the trap,
especially when you've had some early
success with Vibe coding. It's gone off
and built you a first-person shooter.
It's gone off and built you a canban.
And you're thinking, "Oh, wow. This just
works. I'll just yolo. I'll just set it
off. I'll come back later and then I'll
just keep pushing ahead. And it's so
tempting. It is so easy to get lazy, to
start to take it for granted and start
to just sort of trust it. It's like, ah,
it's going to be working. It's it looks
great. If you do that, your your
defenses come down. you let your guard
down and you go several steps forwards
and only then you realize that that
several steps ago it made some terrible
assumption that is complete nonsense and
as a result you've just wasted lots of
time. So, you know, the onus is on you
to be challenging at each step. If if
there's if you're debugging something
and it declares it's found the problem
and fixed it and here's why with lots of
confident bold text, still challenge.
Come in, demand the evidence. Have you
found the root cause? Have you fixed it?
Are you sure? Give me the evidence.
Demonstrate it. Show me the test
results. And then move on. But don't
allow your your guard to come down.
Don't don't just go with it. Even when
you have some successes, one thing's for
sure, you're going to have moments when
you will be blown away by how well it
goes, how much code is built, how
something like the campaign just appears
and is really cool. It's going to be
amazing.
But there will also be times when it's a
fiasco. There will be chaos. There will
be times when it makes a mistake and
then it makes the same mistake again and
you put it in agents.mmd and you say
never ever make this mistake and it
makes it again and you say write a
performance report that says I will
never make this mistake again and read
that performance report every single
time and it still makes a mistake and
when these things happen you it can be
so frustrating. I've had moments when I
have been just just so angry. And what
you have to keep telling yourself and
what you gradually learn is that that is
part of the process. You're hitting up
against limitations of the model that
you're working with. And you need to
find how to work around that. You need
to detect it, manage it, handle it, and
do so with style. This the frustration,
the walls that you can hit against that
is part of the process. These models
give you an enormous leg up in some
ways, but they also have their
downsides. And managing the downsides is
the key path to success. Now, you might
be thinking to yourself, these these
five principles to set me up for
success. They seem to fly in the face of
yolo. It's very much about not just,
hey, I'm going to kick it off. I'm going
to let it have permission. Do whatever
you want. I'm coming back in an hour or
in in a day. That that seems a bit
different. And you're right. Uh, and you
know, you could probably tell I'm not a
huge fan of yolo. There are situations,
as we'll discuss, when it when it makes
sense to do it, but always with a with a
skeptical eye, always be the boss as
much as you can. Even if you yolo, come
back and check everything carefully.
People talk about the trust but verify
mindset that I think I mentioned before.
Uh, you trust it to a certain extent and
then verify very carefully. Indeed, that
is certainly my recipe for success. even
with the really strong models, you need
to be the boss. That's the path to
success. And on that note, I got I got
some some words of wisdom uh for whether
you're from a from a junior background
or from a senior engineer background. I
just have some things to say. If you're
from a coming into this as like new to
programming or a junior engineer on that
that end of the of the continuum, then
first up, you need to use this as an
opportunity to be learning. You want to
take that journey yourself so that you
can become a senior engineer in the
future. And so don't allow yourself to
to to lose sight of the learning
opportunity here. Take this as a way to
challenge and ask questions of the LLM
in order that you can understand what's
happening so that you're learning it
too. So you're making that journey
towards being a senior engineer.
Otherwise, it would be so easy just just
to sort of not not ever acquire that
skill set and just let the model do do
the work which will only lead to
frustration later. And similarly, you
need to be skeptical. The mental model
to have is that you've got this this
assistant that's super eager and that
that will go and hunt on the internet
and research things and do stuff, but
sometimes it's misguided and sometimes
it it's overconfident and makes a
mistake or it it uses band-aids instead
of doing a proper solution. It guesses a
lot. All those kinds of of problems that
we've talked about in the past. And you
have to be you have to be wise to that.
And so come at it with a healthy
skepticism. Ask the right questions.
Always double check even if it seems
confident. Always have that healthy
skepticism in mind and and things will
go much better. And for senior
engineers, to be honest, this tooling is
best suited for you. It's it's harder
for the junior engineers. Sorry, junior
engineers. Uh it's harder because you
just sort of can feel bamboozled by this
thing sometimes and you can't tell if
it's making it up or not. But as a
senior engineer, you can tell. And so,
you're actually in a really good
position to use it. That the the the
point I want to make to you is you need
to to keep in mind that this is a tool
that allows you to build more when used
correctly. I as I don't like to get
caught up in the hype. I don't know that
it's a 10xer, but it's certainly
something that allows you to do more and
build more. And so, my my my ask, my
appeal is that you keep enjoying what
you do. what what excites most of us
engineers is the the fact of building.
And sure, a lot of what gives me
satisfaction is hammering out code and
seeing it run. And so there's a sense
when I work with LLMs that some of that
joy is being taken away from me, but
really it's a trade. It's true that joy
is being taken away of like writing a
line of code, but instead of that, I
have this other joy that I'm able to
build entire systems like front end that
I'm so terrible at. Now I can just have
a front end built just like that. I can
have Terraform scripts written and
things deployed, DevOps stuff that that
I'm on and they can be done really
really fast with LLMs. And so it's given
me all these extra powers I didn't have
before and that allows me to build
faster and building faster is fun. So I
guess my my my ask is to try and keep in
mind that whilst it's taken some things
away, it's given a lot more back. And in
summary, I have a balanced view when it
comes to the productivity improvement
that coding agents bring us. I do see
that there are situations when it's
literally a 10x change in productivity
like the building a canban view in an
X.js app that would take me days maybe
even a week uh whereas it was just a
matter of minutes. So there are clearly
situations where it is a gamecher but
there are situations when that's
definitely not the case. Uh there are
times when it's just an incremental
productivity improvement particularly
with larger projects, legacy projects
with with complex backend changes and
there are situations where it actually
subtracts value. I have had realworld
situations where I've been trying to
build like a streamable HTTP MCP server,
something that's relatively new and
wasn't part of of its of its training uh
data and Claude was messing it up for me
again and again and it took me longer
than it would have taken if I just wrote
it myself. So, it's a mixed bag and
recognizing that it's a mixed bag is a
big part of of of the challenge. You
could come into this, you could have a
lot of success. you could think to
yourself, "Wow, I can change my
estimates to a tenth of what they were."
And then you hit a stumbling block and
then next thing you know, it's it's
everything has been pushed out. So, keep
keep a a healthy understanding of both
the positives and the downsides of
working with coding agents. And in
aggregate, the the main thing to take
away is that I would say it's always a
positive. It's always value ad. Now,
using the top coding agents always
speeds things up. How much it speeds
things up depends hugely on the kind of
task, on the kinds of skills that you
have, on the size of the project, and
many other factors. But you quickly get
to understand what kind of boost you're
going to get once you're a little bit
into that project. Generally speaking,
if you're dealing with a small MVP of a
green field project, you're going to get
a very significant multiplier of your
productivity. In most other cases,
you're talking about a speed
improvement. You're talking about
assistance, but not the kind of 10x
numbers that you sometimes see in all of
the hype.